Hello and welcome back. One of the reasons that image and video
【未完成版本】 大家好 欢迎回来 图像和视频分割是图像处理中的热门研究方向
segmentation is studied so much in image processing is because of its relevance to
其原因之一是 因为它与许多应用领域
multiple applications from the movie industry to medical imaging as we are
从电影业到医学影像 都有关联
going to see in the last week of this class.
在最后一周课程中我们会提到这些
The other reason there are so many studies in this area is because image and
在这个领域有如此丰富的研究 还归因于
video processing is intrinsically a very difficult problem.
图像和视频分割确实是个难题
And, what we are going to do in this video lecture, is basically introduce the
这次视频课程中 我们将介绍
concept of interactive image segmentation.
交互式图像分割的概念
We are going to let the user help us to do the image segmentation.
我们会让用户参与图像分割
So that's basically the topic of, of this lecture, interactive image segmentation.
所以这次课程的主题就是 交互式图像分割
Let me show you a couple of examples. Extreme examples of the difficulty of
我先给出一些例子 用这些极端的例子说明图像分割的难度
image segmentation. This is a really nice image.
这是一幅很棒的图像
If you haven't seen it before, it looks nothing strange to you.
如果你没有见过这幅图 也许它看起来没什么特别的
It's just basically a drawing of a forest.
画的不过是森林
Now if you look very carefully, and I invite you to do that, you start seeing
现在如果你仔细看 请你仔细看一下
faces in this image, faces that are camouflaged.
你会看到图像里 有一些人脸隐藏其中
For example, we see a face here. I hope you can see it - their eyes, nose
比如 这里有一张脸 希望你看出来了 他的眼睛 鼻子 和嘴巴
and mouth. Here, is in our face, here, once the
这里 也有一张脸
eyes, the nose, and the mouth. There is outer phase camouflage here.
这里是眼睛 鼻子 和嘴巴 还有另一张脸隐藏在这里
Eyes, nose, mouth. There's a profile face here, the eyes,
这是眼睛 鼻子 嘴巴 这里有一张侧脸
the nose and the mouth. There is actually a lot of images.
这是眼睛 鼻子 和嘴巴 有许多这样的图像
If you stare at this image for some time, you're going to start discover more and
如果你盯着它看上一会儿 你会发现
more faces that pop-out from this image. Now this is a really challenging image
越来越多的脸突然就出现在图像中
segmentation problem to segment out the faces.
把这些人脸分割出来是非常有挑战性的图像分割问题
It becomes easier if I tell the algorithm, more or less the location of
如果我们或多或少知道一些人脸的位置信息 分割会简单一些
those faces so then the algorithm might be able to find the eyes in those
这样一来 算法可能在这些位置中找到眼睛
locations. Let's see yet another example.
让我们来看另一个例子
You're welcome to pause the video and observe at this image for longer if you
如果你想发现更多的人脸 可以暂停视频 再观察一会图像
wish to discover more and more faces. Let's look at the next example.
看下一个例子吧
Another very interesting drawing. We see a tree.
这也是一幅很有意思的画 我们可以看到一棵树
Here, with the houses in the back, we see a lady.
看到背景的房屋 还有一位女士
Now if you stare at this image, and in particular if you take a bit of distance
如果你凝视这幅图 特别是稍微远离一点屏幕
from the screen. And sometimes if you kind of close your
或者眯着眼睛 图像看上去有点模糊的时候
eyes to blur a bit the image you might actually find that there is a face here.
你可能会发现这里有一张脸
The lady becomes the nose. Here, part of the buildings basically
而女士成了脸上的鼻子 这里的一部分建筑成了眼睛
become the eyes. So once again, how can we tell the image
那么这次 我们如何设计分割算法
segmentation algorithm to segment this very, very difficult image?
来分割这幅复杂的图像呢？
In particular, how can we tell the algorithm if we're interested in the
尤其是 如何告知算法 我们感兴趣的是树 还是人脸
tree, are we interested in the face, are we interested in the nose or the lady?
或者是鼻子 还是女士？
What is foreground? What's background?
哪部分是前景？ 哪部分是背景？
To illustrate what's foreground and what's background, that is a very, very
说明哪里是前景和背景 是非常困难的
difficult problem, let's just see this famous image.
我们来看一下这幅著名的图像
We actually see here. Two profiles, one, two.
我们可以看到两张侧脸 这是第一张 这里第二张
I hope you can also see if you look at the wide region, we see actually a glass.
如果你看向白色区域 希望你也能看到一个玻璃杯
So what is for as forgram, the profile, or the class, it's very hard for the,
那么哪部分是前景 侧脸 还是玻璃瓶？
algorithm in the computer to understand, what is that we're interesting, what's
电脑算法很难理解 图像中哪部分是我们所感兴趣的
interesting in the image for us. So one way of, doing that is, let's the
解决方法之一 就是让用户告诉我们
user. Tell us what's foreground, what's
哪里是前景 哪里是背景
background. Let us use the user, basically, which is
我们让用户
the real client of this and the one that it is interested in the segmentation, let
也就是对分割感兴趣的客户
us use the user to give us a bit of information about the image.
让用户告诉我们关于图像的一些信息
And the way to do that. That we're going to explore is basically
我们需要做的是
we're going to ask the user. To mark very simple scribbles.
请用户简单地涂抹 进行标记
The user is going to come and just scribble.
用户只需要大致涂抹
Here's a story line, but just can be any mark in the image, as we're going to see
这里是用直线 但是也可以用任意的标记 之后我们会见到
later, and say, you know, I want to call this background.
然后指定这是背景
Another student said, I want to call this foregram.
而另一个人说 这是前景
Now go and segment it. So that's all what we are going to ask
现在进行分割 以上是现阶段我们需要从用户处得知的
from the user at this stage. We might ask more, later on.
稍后我们还需要询问更多信息
Once of course, we segment it out we can do different things, like putting new
当然 一旦我们分割出前景和背景 还可以干点别的事
images in the background. But it's very important that we are
比如说在背景放入新的图像 从用户那儿得到帮助是很重要的
going to get help from the user. We shouldn't be asking a lot of help.
但是我们不能询问太多信息
We shouldn't be asking the user to go around and basically completely mark the
我们不能让用户完整地标记出物体的边界
boundary of the object. Then there's not much left for the
那样就没什么活儿给电脑干了
computer to do and that's very tedious, which is still done sometimes, but it's
那会是很乏味的 有时候用户仍然愿意帮忙
very tedious work for the user. We want very little interaction that can
但是那太繁琐乏味了 我们只需要少量的但是帮助巨大的交互
help us a lot. How can we exploit these scribbles?
我们如何利用这些涂抹呢？
So I'm going to illustrate that. I'm going to tell you a particular
我接下来会说明这个 我会告诉大家一个特定的流程来利用这些信息
pipeline to exploit these. But the underlying ideas are very common
这其中的基本思想
in multiple, multiple techniques for image segmentation that you can find in
和文献中的许多图像分割技术都是相通的
the literature. So the user has given us hints of what's
用户提示我们哪部分是前景
foreground, that we see here. And what's background?
也就是这里 还告诉我们哪部分是背景
We can basically go and look at all the pixels that the user has marked as
我们考虑用户标记为前景的所有像素
foreground. We can draw the histogram.
画出其直方图
We can draw the distribution of those pixels.
画出这些像素的分布
We can do basically the same for the background, so we end up with that:
对背景部分也是这样处理 所以我们画出前景的分布
Distribution of foreground, we end up with the distribution of background.
还有背景的分布
Very often the background has much more variability than the foreground.
通常 背景的像素值分布比前景的变化性更大
Now, if you now give me a pixel. I can, compute what's a probability of
现在 如果你告诉我一个像素值 我可以从用户标记的分布中
being in the foreground. What's a probability of being in the
算出它属于前景的概率有多大
background. From these, distributions.
而它属于背景的概率又是多少
That the user mark. Once again, all what I'm using are the
再重复一下 我们利用的是
pixels that the user marked as foreground.
用户标记为前景的像素
And the pixels that a user marked as background.
和用户标记为背景的像素
We can actually normalize this. So here, we use C to stand for the vector
我们可以进行归一化 这里用c表示彩色空间中的向量
in color space. It can be RGB, red, green, blue.
它可以是RGB向量 即红 绿 蓝
It can be other color space. It doesn't matter.
也可以是其他彩色空间向量 这不重要
It's whatever are the colors, just under the scribbles that the user has marked.
它就是用户进行涂抹时 标记的颜色
And again, we have these distributions. And we can predict the probability of a
然后 我们得到这些分布 可以预测一个像素
pixel being foreground or background, which is just the probability of being
属于前景或者背景的概率 也就是属于前景的概率
foreground and we normalize by both foreground or background.
然后我们除以前景或背景的概率之和 进行归一化
So, for example, a pixel that was marked by the user as being foreground.
比如说 一个被用户标记为前景的像素
It would have a very high probability, that pixel value.
该像素值会对应一个非常大的概率值
basically, once again, this is just a particular illustration.
再次说明 这是个具体的例子
The basic idea is that we use the distribution of the foreground and the
基本的思路是 我们利用前景和背景的分布
distribution of the background to tell the computer.
告诉电脑
You know, pixels that are similar to the colors that the user has marked as
与用户标记为前景的颜色相似的像素
foreground, you should try to call them foreground.
我们应该称它们为前景
Pixels that are similar to the color of what the user has marked as background,
而与用户标记为背景的颜色相似的像素
you should try to call them background. So, now we have kind of an idea of what
应该称之为背景 现在我们知道什么是前景
to call foreground, what to call background.
什么是背景
And. If we just take, basically, this formula
如果我们利用这个公式
and we draw that. We are going to get this.
画出一幅图像 我们会得到这个图像
Which is already a very interesting segmentation.
这已经是很有意思的分割了
Just by looking this exercise and looking at this image.
单是看这个操作 这一幅图
We can almost find the object of interest.
我们差不多可以找到感兴趣的物体
Basically, what the user told us is the object of interest, which is the cat.
这里用户告诉我们 他所感兴趣的物体 就是这只猫
Now there's something interesting to observe here.
这里还应注意到一些有趣的事
So, the higher the value here, the more probability of being foreground, based on
基于用户给我们的信息 这里的像素值越高 就越有可能是前景
what the user told us. So why do you think that these eyes are
那这双暗色的眼睛如何标记呢
basically very dark, meaning have very high probability of being background and
暗色意味着它很可能是背景
very low probability of being foreground, and that's because they're very dark, and
而属于前景的概率很小 因为它们颜色很暗
look, also here we have very dark pixels, so if we just look at the pixels that the
而且这里也有很暗的像素 所以如果我们只考虑用户标记的像素
user has marked. That's not enough information for us.
这点信息对于我们是不够用的
Because they might be inside the object of interest some pixels that look as the
因为一些看起来是背景的像素 可能在我们感兴趣的物体内部
background. So we need to do a bit more.
所以我们还要进一步处理
What can we do? Let us see that next.
我们要怎样做呢？ 接下来就会看到
What we're going to do, is we're going to basically try to find.
我们需要做的是 试着找出图像中的所有像素
All the pixels in the image compare them with the probability of being foreground
将它们作为前景的概率和作为背景的概率相比较
and the probability of being background. And then we are going to make a decision.
然后再做决定
How we're going to do that comparison? Using something which is called geodesic.
我们如何比较？ 这要用到测地线 (geodesic)
Distance. And this is something that you basically
这也是我们每天都会用到的
do every day. When you go to work, when you go in your
当我们去上班的时候 在家里从房间走到厨房的时候
house from your room to the kitchen, you're basically traveling a path.
我们都需要经过一段路程
And you're going to try to travel, all the time, the path of minimal effort.
而且我们总是会走最短的路线
So if you want to go from your room to the kitchen, and you don't want to, you
所以 如果想要从房间走到厨房
want to get there as fast as possible, you're going the shortest path.
想要尽可能快到达 我们就会走最短的路线
Now sometimes does that path has an obstacle.
有时候这个路线中会有障碍物
So for example a wall. You cannot go through the wall.
比如说一道墙 我们不能穿墙而过
You have to go around the wall. So if you draw a map of your office or
我们要绕过墙 如果画一幅办公室或家里的地图
house, there are certain. Regions that are very easy to go through.
有些区域是很容易通过的
Certain regions that are much harder to go through.
而一些区域会比较难通过
So when you want to go from one point to another you might not be able to go in a
【未完成版本】 所以 当我们想要从一点到达另一个点 可能没办法走直线
straight line. For example if there is a wall, you're
举例来说 如果前方有一道墙 你就必须绕开它
going to have to basically go around it. And the basic idea is that every region
所以基本原理是这样的 每条路径上的不同区域都会有自己的权值
in the path has a weight. And that weight, we're going to call it
用W表示
W. What we're going to do is, we're going to
我们接下来要做的是
go to every pixel in the image and we're going to compute the minimal path.
遍历图像中的所有像素 计算到达前景涂抹
To let foregram prevail, the minimal path, to the background screening.
和到达背景涂抹的最短路径
Once we have that, we're going to decide if its foreground or background according
一旦得到了这两条最短路径 我们就可以比较路径的长短来判断给定像素是前景还是背景
to which path is shorter. So I have to tell you, what are we
所以我必须告诉你 到底什么是W
going to use as w. Before that, let me just make a remark,
在那之前 我先做一个标注
that this can be computer very fast, actually, linear time.
计算路径的效率非常高 实际上 时间复杂度是线性的
Visiting every pixel of the image only once you can compute that.
只要把每个像素遍历一遍
Distance. The path.
就可以计算出最短加权路径
Basically, this formula to the foreground and to the background.
就是利用这个距离公式
So this is not very difficult computation.
所以这不是非常困难的计算
This is based on extensions of techniques that are called Dios Track techniques.
该算法基于新近发展的Dijkstra算法 (Dijkstra technique)
And they are very standard techniques in graph a, a theory.
那也是图论中的标准技术
And we're going to discuss them a bit more next week when we talk about partial
下周讲到偏微分方程时 我们会继续深入讨论
differential equations. For now, all that I want you to know.
现在 大家只需要知道
Is that this computation, of what's a minimal effort, from traveling from, a
这个式子可以计算出某一点像素到任一涂抹区域的最短加权路径
pixel, to any one of the scribbles with a weight that I'm going to define in a
接下来我会介绍这个权值的定义
second. That minimal effort can be computed
计算最短路径是非常快速的
extremely, extremely fast, mmk, basically can be done in real time.
基本能够实时完成
So what's W? Which is computed thanks to the
那什么是W呢？ 它根据用户涂抹区域的
scribbles, the distribution of colors, so that's what we're going to use.
颜色分布计算而来
We're basically going to use. That probability that we just computed.
因此我们将使用刚刚算出的概率来定义W
And what we are going to think is the following.
而我们要思考的是以下问题
If, from the pixel I'm seeking, going to the scribble, the probability of being
如果 从当前像素到涂抹区域的路径上
foreground doesn't change too much. That means that I'm probably a foreground
前景的概率没有多大变化 这就意味着这个像素很可能是前景像素
pixel. If I can keep going for myself to the
如果我继续遍历到达前景涂抹区域的路径
foreground scribble and the probability of foreground doesn't change meaning the
而路径上的前景概率不变 那就意味着梯度不变
gradient doesn't change. Remember gradient is the difference
还记得梯度表示的是连续像素之间的区别么？
between consecutive pixels. In the direction of the past.
在路径方向上
So this is the curve. So I'm going to travel the curve.
这表示路径曲线 我将遍历这条曲线
I'm basically going to go from every place.
从图像中每一个像素到涂抹区域
In the image to a scribble. I'm going to look for a path, and I'm
我们找到一条路径
going to say, is my probability of being foreground changing a lot around this
判断该路径上 前景的概率改变是否很大？
path? If it's changing a lot, I'm going to pay
如果改变了很多 那么我将付出很大的代价通过该路径
a big price. If it's not changing a lot, I'm going to
反之 我只会付出很小的代价
pay a small price. Then I can take another path.
然后我也可以选另一条路径
I'm going to see which path, is, shorter, with this weight, and I'm going to do
根据相应权重 判断哪一条路径更短
this same, for another point, in this scribble, I'm going basically do that
并且对涂抹区域中的另外一点 我们也做同样的计算
for, every point in this scribble, so I'm computing to, every single point, in this
实际上我们会对涂抹区域中所有的点
scribble. What's the, path, where my probability of
根据前景概率计算 哪一条路径最短
fil, be in foreground, is, smaller, than I have to do basically the same, for this
然后 对背景区域的涂抹
scribbles. Of background.
我们也做同样的计算
So for this pixel I'm going to say what's the probability, whats it cost of getting
所以对于这个像素 我要知道它到背景区域的路径上的
to the background and then I'm going to compare that.
概率和代价 接着我就会比较得出它是前景还是背景
So in pictures when we do this computation which again can be done
所以当我们在图片中做这些计算 再次说明计算的效率非常高
extremely fast. We have the scribbles.
我们知道了涂抹区域
This was the probability we computed before, this image.
这幅图像表示的是我们之前计算过的概率
This is an image where the colors blue means low.
而这幅图像中 蓝色表示属于前景的概率小
Red means large. Same here.
红色表示概率大 这里也一样
Basically blue. Going to red we are basically from small
蓝色到红色的变化 表示概率由小变大
to large. We are basically saying that every pixel
也就是说 这儿的每一个像素
here has a very large distance basically to the foreground, but pixels here have
到前景区域的距离很大 但是这儿的像素
very low distance to the foreground and the inverse here.
到前景的距离很短 这幅图则相反
So I want to repeat that once again, we first computed the probability based on
我想回顾一下 我们首先依据用户标记区域的颜色分布
the color distributions that the user has marked for us.
计算出概率
Then we say okay and I'm just going to use a figure to illustrate that.
接下来…我用一张图片来说明
We basically say from every pixel. In the image.
我们从图像上的每一点开始
They just compute curves that start at the pixel, finish at the scribble.
找出它到涂抹区域的曲线
And let's see what's the cost of traveling that curve.
然后让我们看看通过这条曲线 花费的代价
And the cost is given by this function. The less it changes the probability of
代价是由这个函数计算的
being foreground, the lower the cost. We do the same to the background for
前景概率变化越小 代价越小 对于图中每一个像素到背景涂抹也做同样计算
every pixel. And then we say, is it cheaper for you to
接着我们判断 到达前景涂抹的代价
get to the foreground scribble, than it is for you to get to the background
比到背景所需的代价更小吗？
scribble, then I call you a foreground pixel.
如果是这样 我们称它为前景像素
If it's the other way around, I call you a background pixel.
如果相反 那么它就是背景像素
There you see all the computations are done computing this minimal effort curve
你可以发现 找到图像中的最小代价曲线只需要经过一次计算
gone by the image only once. Once you have done that for every pixel,
一旦完成对每个像素的计算
basically you draw the boundary. Of the probability of being background or
基本上你就能画出前景和背景的概率边界
foreground, and you get your very, very nice segmentation.
完成一次漂亮的图像分割
Relatively simple algorithm. Now, we can do a bit more.
这是相当简单的算法 现在 我们可以做得更好
This was based on scribbles that were marked somewhere so there was a
这个算法是以用户涂抹为基础的
foreground scribble here. And there were a few background scribbles
所以这儿会有前景涂抹 周围有背景涂抹
around. But now we have a first estimate of where
但现在 在第一次估计
our boundary between foreground and background should be.
前景和背景的初步边界后
We can explore that in a second stage which is fully automatic.
我们可以第二阶段 探究一个完全自动化的操作
And the basic idea is very simple. Okay, let's just go back.
并且它的原理非常简单 现在回顾一下
This was what our first estimate was. Let's just move inside, the object a bit,
这是我们的初步边界 我们将边界向物体内移动一点
and let's move outside the object a bit full automatic fashion, and we can call
再把边界向外移动一点 这些操作是全自动化的
this now. A foreground scribble.
然后我们可以将这块区域称为前景涂抹
Not the one that we mark before, we call this one now, which is automatically
不是先前用户的涂抹 而是现在自动计算得出的区域
computed, we call it a foreground scribble and we call this a background
我们把它称为前景涂抹 再将这个称为背景涂抹
scribble. And I can do my algorithm once again but
然后再次使用算法
I can do the estimation of the probability of being foreground.
但是现在我可以用这个十分接近边界的涂抹
Now based on that scribble which is very, very close to the boundary, so it
再次估计前景概率
probably have better information, about where that boundary should be. And
因而能得出更精确的边界位置
actually moreover, we can actually do that locally.
此外 我们可以只进行局部计算
If I want to refine this boundary, I can only look at this scribble, and this
如果我想让边界更精确 可以只考虑这里和这里的涂抹
piece of the scribble, compute my probability and refine it then go into a
计算概率 细化这里的边界
different region, and also only use that to refine this and so on. So I can travel
接着进入另一个区域继续细化 以此类推
around my first estimate, get new estimates of what should be foreground
所以我可以遍历初步边界 得到前景区域和背景区域的新的估计
and what should be background, and get a really, really very accurate segmentation
然后就能得到非常精确的图像分割
from that. So, we'll run twice the algorithm, first
所以 我们运行两次算法
we let the user help us to find this distribution.
第一次 让用户帮助我们找到这个分布
Second, we let the initial stage to tell us how to compute that distribution, and
接着 我们通过第一次得知如何计算更精确的边界
then we get a really, really nice segmentation as you can see, we can
于是 如你所见
basically get very accurate at the boundary.
我们得到了非常精确的边界
Very basically, we get the errors and we get really, really good results with
甚至精确到猫的毛发 得到非常好的分割结果
that. So, let me give you a few examples of
让我列举一些例子
this and we see them basically here. We have in every role examples and we can
看这里 在每一行的例子中
see this prevail. This is the binary segmentation.
我们可以看见这些涂抹 这些都是二值化分割
And then as we already talked, I can put it in a different background.
正如我们提到过的 我可以将它放置到另外的背景上
Here basically different images different images so basically every row has a
这里有不同的图像 而每一行中都是不同的例子
different example its very important when you do any image process algorithm that
当你需要设计能适用于大量不同数据的图像处理算法时
works for a lot of data you don't want to design an algorithm that works for only
验证多种数据是非常重要的 我们不会只为一种类型的数据设计算法
one type of data you want to be as global as possible unless you have a very
而是尽可能地让算法普适化
particular application in mind and then its very important to show that it works
除非你的算法有特殊的应用 否则验证算法能适用于多种图像非常重要
for a large variety of images. Now you may wonder, what happens.
现在你也许想知道 该算法会遇到什么情况
Do I need the user to be an expert? Do I need the user to basically be.
我们要求用户很专业吗？
You know. Have complete knowledge of the algorithms
我们要求用户完全理解算法
and mark these scribbles exactly where they should be to give me the hints.
然后精确地标记这些区域 好给我们提示信息？
Of course, if that's needed, then this algorithm is not very useful.
当然 如果需要的话 那这个算法就不实用了
We want the user to basically work with the algorithm in a very relaxed fashion,
我们想让用户非常轻松地与算法交互
so. Here is just an example that this type of
这里有一个例子 说明这种算法的强大
algorithm inside normally very robust. So we have the same image, and very
我们有相同的图像
different foreground, scribbles the blues and very different background scribbles,
和非常不同的蓝色的前景涂抹 和绿色的背景涂抹
the greens. And we see that basically the results are
我们可以看到处理结果是相同的
the same. You see the boundary between foreground
所有图像中前景和背景的边界
and background being basically identical in all of the images.
基本上完全一致
So we want really the user to be very, very friendly with the images and the
我们想让用户融洽地操作图像
algorithm not to ask too much of the user.
而不要让算法对用户的要求过高
Actually, it ask very little. It basically, all that the algorithm asks
实际上 这个算法的要求非常低
is the user to say, please mark me foreground and basically go and please
它只是请用户标记前景和背景
mark me, background. I used a different colors in my pen than
我用不同颜色的笔在图像中做标记
in the image, but the message is very clear.
好让标记足够清晰
So, this is an example of interactive image segmentation the user has help us.
这就是一个用户参与的 交互式图像分割的例子
We're going to see a couple of additional videos.
我们还会有另外一组视频
One, we are basically going to be running this inside Adobe Photoshop, one of the
在一个视频中 我们将在Adobe Photoshop中 演示这种交互式算法
examples. The other, we're going to do interactive
另外一个视频中  我们将在Adobe的另一款产品中
video segmentation in one of the next videos is one of the basically algorithms
进行交互式视频分割
inside one of Adobe's products that I'm going to give you details about this.
稍后我会告诉你们更多的细节
So I'll see you in the next videos. Thank you very much.
【未完成版本】 那么下一个视频再见 谢谢